Finding Aid for Department of Anthropology (University of Michigan) Records 1927-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Anthropology (University of Michigan) records 1927-1983
University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.
2 linear feet
Established in 1929, the University of Michigan Department of Anthropology provides instruction in ethnology, archaeology, biological anthropology, and linguistics, and is consistently ranked among the top academic programs in anthropology in the country. The records include correspondence from James B. Griffin's tenure as chair (1972-1975), meeting minutes, memos and general correspondence, and descriptions of degree requirements and courses.
03100 Bimu 2
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology (donor no. 9273 ) in January 2003.
The records are open for research.
The University of Michigan Department of Anthropology was established in 1929 by Carl E. Guthe, director of the university's Museum of Anthropology, and Julian Steward. Administratively, the department was originally part of the museum, and housed within the museum's facilities. Steward left soon after the department began offering courses, but two additional faculty members were added over the next ten years, Leslie A. White in 1930 and Mischa Titiev in 1936. By 1940 the department offered 16 courses, an undergraduate major, and a master of arts program.
During and immediately after World War II, the department began to expand more rapidly, although founding member Carl Guthe left the university in 1944. Three curators from the Museum of Anthropology, James B. Griffin (Guthe's successor as museum director), Volney H. Jones, and Emerson Greenman, were the first additions to the department, in 1945 and 1946. The academic program was designed to prepare students in all four subfields of anthropology (ethnology, linguistics, archaeology and biological anthropology), and faculty were added strategically in all areas. By 1948, the department offered a Ph.D. program, and by 1955, its faculty had risen to 15, offering 75 courses.
More faculty and courses were steadily added in the coming years. By 2002, the department enrolled over 5000 student per year in undergraduate and graduate courses and had more than 50 faculty members. A number of anthropology faculty have joint appointments with other departments and programs at the university, including history, women's studies, and the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies (CAAS).
The department moved several times over the years to accommodate its growth. In 1954 the department took up offices in the basement of Angell Hall, though faculty from the museum retained their offices in the museum. The department later relocated its administrative offices to the LS&A building in 1981, and to West Hall in 2003.
Ethnology has traditionally been the most well-represented anthropology subfield in the department's faculty and courses, but the Museum of Anthropology's national prominence has assured that archaeology has also been very strong. In addition to the faculty members already mentioned, the long list of prominent anthropologists and archaeologists that have been associated with the department either as faculty or students includes Roy Rappaport, Eric Wolf, Richard MacNeish, Marshall Sahlins, Albert Spaulding, Lewis Binford, Ruth Behar, and Henry T. Wright.
Today the department offers joint graduate programs in Anthropology and History, Anthropology and Social Work, Evolution and Behavior, and Culture and Cognition, as well as undergraduate, master's, and doctoral courses and degrees. It is consistently ranked one of the top anthropology departments in the country. More information is available on the department's website at http://www.lsa.umich.edu/anthro/.
(Additional information about the Department of Anthropology may be found in the papers of individual faculty members, including Leslie A. White, James B. Griffin, and Roy A. Rappaport, all available at the Bentley Historical Library.)
The University of Michigan Department of Anthropology record group is arranged into five series: Chair Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, Memos and General Correspondence Weekly Bulletin, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; Anthropology--Study and teaching.
Contributors:
Griffin, James B. (James Bennett), 1905-1997; Guthe, Carl E. (Carl Eugen), 1893-1974
- Chair Correspondence (James B. Griffin)
  The Chair Correspondence series, 1971-1975 (0.5 linear feet), contains material from James B. Griffin's term as chair of the department from 1972 to 1975. A substantial portion of this correspondence is relatively routine, concerning personnel matters or outside information requests, though the correspondence with Frank H.T. Rhodes, the dean of LS&A during this time, does provide a broader overview of the activities of the department.
  - Bachtiar, Harsja 1973 (Box 1)
  - Beardsley, Richard K. 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Bigony, Bea 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Burnor, Duane 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - B -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Carroll, Vern 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Chair Appointment Details 1972 (Box 1)
  - C -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Davies, Philip E. 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - D -- Miscellaneous 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - E -- Miscellaneous 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Edwards, Richard 1972 (Box 1)
  - Faulkingham, Ralph H. 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Fischer, John L. 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Frisancho, A. Roberto 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - F -- Miscellaneous 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Garn, Stanley 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Gedney, William 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - G -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - H -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - I -- Miscellaneous 1974 (Box 1)
  - J -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - K -- Miscellaneous 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Lehman, Edward J. 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Luton, Henry 1973 (Box 1)
  - L -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - M -- Miscellaneous 1971-1975 (Box 1)
  - N -- Miscellaneous 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Orr, Kenneth G. 1973 (Box 1)
  - Overberger, Charles G. 1972 (Box 1)
  - Owusu, Maxwell 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - O -- Miscellaneous 1973 (Box 1)
  - Peacock, James L. 1973 (Box 1)
  - P -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Rappaport, Roy 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Rhodes, Frank H.T. 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - R -- Miscellaneous 1971-1975 (Box 1)
  - Sahlins, Marshall 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Stuart, John R. 1973 (Box 1)
  - S -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - T -- Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - V -- Miscellaneous 1973 (Box 1)
  - Wolpoff, Wright and Farrand to Africa 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - W -- Miscellaneous 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Yengoyan, Aram 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Y to Z -- Miscellaneous 1973 (Box 1)
- Meeting Minutes
  The Meeting Minutes series, 1945-1983 (0.25 linear feet), provides a record of decisions made in department faculty meetings from 1945 to 1983, as the department grew steadily to national prominence. Not all minutes are included in this series; some are missing, and some may be found elsewhere in the record group. For the period from 1976 through early 1980, faculty meeting minutes can be found in the department's Weekly Bulletin (held here in the series of the same name).
  - 1945-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1976 (Box 3)
  - 1980-1982 (Box 3)
- Memos and General Correspondence
  The Memos and General Correspondence series, 1945-1983 (0.5 linear feet), contains memoranda and other materials intended for wide distribution within the department, such as curriculum and course information, student and staff rosters, and general announcements. The series also includes a small amount of correspondence reflecting the relationship between the department and the Museum of Anthropology.
  - 1945-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 2)
  - 1968 (Box 2)
  - 1969 (Box 2)
  - 1970 (Box 2)
  - 1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1972 (Box 2)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - 1978-1983 (Box 2)
- Weekly Bulletin
  The Weekly Bulletin series, 1976-1980 (6 folders), is comprised of issues of the department's newsletter, which also includes meeting minutes, announcements and other information about the activities of the department. Distribution of the newsletter was limited to faculty and administrative staff.
  - 1976, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1977 (Box 3)
  - 1978 (Box 3)
  - 1979 (Box 3)
  - 1980 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series, 1927-1975 (5 folders), includes a small amount of material related to the department's Executive Committee, a program evaluation written for LS&A in 1974, and the "Guide for Graduate Study in Anthropology," a serial publication documenting the academic requirements of the department's graduate program. Of particular historical importance in the series is a comprehensive letter Carl E. Guthe wrote to Dean Alfred H. Lloyd of the Graduate School in 1927 that outlines the ideology for a future program for teaching anthropology at the university, including suggested courses.
  - Bibliography in Anthropology 1954 (Box 2)
  - Examination Questions 1929-1960s (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee 1971-1975 (Box 2)
  - Guide for Graduate Study in Anthropology 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - Outline for Teaching Anthropology at U-M 1927 (written by Carl E. Guthe for Dean Alfred H. Lloyd of the Graduate School) (Box 2)
  - Program Evaluation Report (for LS&A) 1974 (Box 2)